Ravisekhar R

Bangalore, India

Career Summary

Data Scientist with 3 years of industrial experience in aviation domain and strong academic exposure to AI and Business Analytics | First place in online Hackathon, "Hack of all trades", conducted by Great Learning

Key skills

Machine Learning, Text Analytics, Data Engineering, Predictive Analytics, Image analytics, Data Visualization Tools/Languages - Python, SQL, R, Web development using Flask/RShiny, Tableau, PowerBI, Alteryx

Work experience

Cyient Insights *Data Scientist*

July 2018 - Present

Hyderabad, Telegana

Contractor at Collins Aerospace, Bangalore.....

- Worked closely with operations team and predictive health maintenance team for development of digital solutions powered with data analytic capabilities. The deployed solutions were able to automate the conventional manual process cycle of data cleaning, merging and visualisation. The proposed architecture brought down the process time of several days of manual work to just a couple of minutes
- o Skills and Tools: Python, SAP Automation, Data Visualization, Tableau, PowerBI, Microsoft SQL Server, Python-Flask

Text recognition on aircraft tail and engine data plates.....

- Built an end to end solution for an android application to recognize text from images of aircraft tail and data plates of aircraft engines using pre-trained models for object detection and recognition
- The visual search based application was developed to reduce the time spent in manual information search (about aircraft parts) in the operational work centres
- o Skills and Tools: AWS Rekognition, Tesser-OCR, Python, OpenCV, Text Detection, Text Recognition, Android programming

Mu Sigma Business Solutions

August 2013 - October 2013

Trainee Decision Scientist

Bengaluru, Karnataka

- Worked on a project from the retail industry domain to identify the factors determining the scan time delay at checkout counters
- Based on the data provided, the products that caused maximum scanning delay at checkout counters were identified and reported to the client to take necessary actions to reduce the scan time and improve the efficiency at checkout counters
- o Skills and Tools: SAS, SQL, R-studio and Microsoft Excel

Position of responsibility

IIT Madras, NPTEL, IIT Mandi

January 2015 - January 2018

Teaching Assistant

Chennai, Tamil Nadu

- Mentored BTech students in computational engineering (C programming) lab and Software Engineering lab
- o Designed content for programming assessment and involved in evaluation, grading of quizzes and assignments and also developed automated python scripts for evaluating programming assignment submissions
- o Front end management of an online course titled "Constraint Satisfaction in AI" on NPTEL

Key Projects in Data Science

1. E-Commerce product recommendation based on customer reviews

December 2019 - March 2020

Capstone Project

Great Learning

- The objective of the project was to perform an EDA on a dataset of women's clothing reviews, understand the various customer review patterns and product affinities, and build various models to predict product recommendations.
- o Skills and Tools: Text Analytics, Sentiment Analysis, Random Forest, Logistic Regression, R, Google Data Studio

2. Factoid QA Engine For Unstructured Data

May-June 2017

IASNLP 2017 Summer School Project

IIIT Hyderabad

- o The objective of this project was to build a system that can transform unstructured data (like Wikipedia pages) into semi-structured form and designing a natural language question answering system over it.
- o Skills and Tools: Text extraction, Triple Generation, NLP, Knowledge Graph, ReVerb, Spacy, Python, NetworkX
- o Remark: The project won the third best project award at IASNLP 2017 conducted at IIIT, Hyderabad.

3. Building a supervised model to cross-sell personal loans

July 2019

Data Mining - Course Project

Great Learning

- o The objective of this exercise was to build a model using random forests to figure out profitable segments to target for cross-selling personal loans. A pilot campaign data of 20000 customers was used which included several demographic and behavioral variables. The model was further validated and a deployment strategy was recommended based on the customer pattern identified.
- o Skills and Tools: Random Forest, Kmeans clustering, Data Mining, R-studio

4. Acquiring planning domains from procedural texts *MS Thesis*

January 2017 - July 2018

IIT Madras

- o The work focused on illustrating a method to generate planning domain models in **PDDL language** from domain represented in procedural text format , like cooking recipes, and model them as domains involving temporal and metric parameters.
- Skills and Tools: Automated Planning, PDDL, NLP, Web mining, Text extraction, Word clustering, WordNet, Python,
 Spacy

Education

Program	Institution	%/CGPA	Year
PGP-BABI	Great Lakes & University of Texas	Excellent	2019-20
B.Tech. (Computer Science and Engg.)	SCTCE, University of Kerala, Kerala	8.02	2009-13
XII - ISC	Christ Nagar Hr.Sec. School, Trivandrum	88	2008-09
X - ICSE	Christ Nagar Hr.Sec. School, Trivandrum	89.9	2006-07

Achievements and Awards

- 1. Most Valued Performer Bronze awarded by Cyient (September -2020, March-2020).
- 2. **Star TA Award** for outstanding contribution as a Teaching Assistant by Department of Computer Science and Engineering, IIT Madras (November-2017).
- 3. **Best Project Third Prize** at eighth IIIT-H Advanced Summer School on NLP conducted by IIIT, Hyderabad (IASNLP-2017).